Okay, we're going to call the one that Ryan was going to count so maybe for a day's day and time.
I didn't do this proclamation to clarify April 16th, 2019.
Northeastern Oklahoma and in college-sintennial recognition.
And we're going to start this out by asking Coach Amanda Jones to come up.
And if you would tell us a little bit about your team and what they've accomplished this year,
if you'll feel the podium, and then we'll present the proclamation and take a picture.
I'll pre-spine the native opportunity to brag on this.
Before I get started, I'd like to introduce the two ladies on the front row that I have here with me.
We have Ms. McKinsey Converch. She's our department chair of the Agricultural Department.
And then next to her, is my partner in crime in terms of coaching, and that's Ms. Josie Reed.
We brought her on this year, and she's just been nothing but amazing on helping these guys get us qualified to nationals.
So, we brought her on a few Ann Voice.
When we come up here to the front row, I'll introduce you guys a little bit about this year.
So, I'll kind of introduce who we have with us here today.
And so first we have Ms. Anne O'Wolfy. She's one of our open riders, and she's kind of our go-to girl in the rain.
She's going to be riding for the team at Nationals in the Rain and Division.
And she's from Sky to Oklahoma.
And then we have Ms. Caitlin Cates. She's from Bloomville, Missouri.
And she's going to be riding for the team in the intermediate division.
And then we have Ms. Caleb Burns. She's from Lola, Oregon.
And she's going to be competing individually in the walk-truck division.
And then next, we have Ms. Emma Kim. She's from Prior Oklahoma.
And what's kind of a fun story about these two is they were championed reserve champion in the walk-truck division at some of my finals.
And so we got two of the four spots in terms of going to Nationals.
So, she'll be going to Nationals in the walk-truck division.
And then we have Mr. Derek Strahan. He's the one boy that's all in all the girls down.
On the team, Derek is from Columbia, Missouri.
And he's going to be representing the team in the beginner division.
And then we have Ms. Arianna Horton. She's from Easton, Kansas.
She's going to be representing the team in the advanced division.
And then next, we have Ms. Karla Kofora. Karla's going to be riding in three classes at Nationals.
Karla is, again, one of our other open riders.
And Karla qualified individually in the raining and the horsemanship.
And then Karla is also going to be riding for the team in the individual horsemanship.
And then next in Karla, she's from St. Amat, Louisiana.
And the next we have Ms. Seer, McCullough, Seer, qualified individually in the novice division.
She's from Knoxville, Iowa. And then ending the line as Ms. Bailey suffers.
She's from Ozark, Missouri, and she's going to be writing for the team in the novice division.
And so why our year has been so excellent this year is these guys had an undefeated regular season.
Going into our qualifications of getting us two nationals.
And so the very first show we go to after our regular season is regionals.
And we had 15 kids that qualified individually is two regionals of our team, one regionals.
And then after that we then had to go to Finland, Ohio for semi-finals.
And they were the seated national champions of last year.
So the little intimidating going into their kind of venue for our semi-finals.
And we had to be the top three teams to make it to the nationals.
And we were the only junior college there competing to make it to the nationals.
And these guys were reserved to my final champions behind Finley, Ohio to make it to the nationals.
And then we had the couple that made it individually as well.
And so this is a very first year that we've ever qualified to team for two nationals.
We've always had some individual riders to make it.
But this was kind of a big deal for us to get the team through.
And so we're really excited and these guys are working really hard to represent any of you.
Well, in Syracuse, New York.
It's where we will be going for the nationals.
So that is the team.
And that's kind of our year.
And again, we just really appreciate you guys having us here this evening.
And we're seeing this proclamation on behalf of any of you.
We're going to give you a heads up.
Yeah.
So I'm going to, why don't we step into the meeting.
Okay.
And I'll present this to you.
Come on.
Let's see how we'll do this.
And you like this.
Okay.
We're going to get the entire group in.
All right.
Thank you.
Congratulations.
No, we're certainly welcome to stay for the whole meeting if you want, but we would also understand
this.
I'm going to be studying all of these.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you all again.
Congratulations.
You know, I wanted to ask do the horses go to New York as well and do a
The interesting thing is when they compete, they are assigned a horse and they don't know the horse.
They don't know the horse.
And then we have to go through the routine on a completely strange horse that they've never been able to do.
Calacarodia.
I guess.
Yeah.
Wow.
It's amazing.
Yeah.
There was a Louisiana in the group.
Well, that's the other way.
They're from all over.
Yeah.
Okay.
Thank you.
Everyone, let's move on to item three.
Proclamation declaring April 18, 2019, Coleman Theatre and a Versary Recognition.
And for everybody watching, if you're not aware, we're having a birthday party.
First day, not at the coalman in Jordan.
I'm going to let you speak to the specifics of that, if you will.
If you'll come up and, or Shannon, whoever doesn't matter.
And so we are having a birthday party.
We will be showing the Wizard of Oz at 710, when we're going to start the movie.
From 5 to 6, we have a invitation, a buy invitation reception for some of our donors and our board.
And just some, some folks that have been so influential over the years with all the restoration.
And just what has gone on with the Coleman for a long, long time.
And Jane Nalsford will be speaking about early, early years as we began restoration.
And so it's just going to be a night.
People are going to come with us as characters out of the Wizard of Oz.
My little theatre will be supplying some characters for a photo of Shannon.
My name is Ann.
We're green.
We're wearing green for the Emerald City, if you're not dressed as a character.
We will have birthday cake for everybody.
How many times, how many tickets, every soul for the movie?
We're about seven and a half times.
Seven and a half times.
The tickets are a dollar of peace because that is what a ticket was when the Coleman opened for a movie.
and so that's part of the retro part and anyway it's going to be a fun fun night and if you
have chance to go, please come. Okay, I am going to present this proclamation and to
Jenny and Jordan. This is Jordan Moyni's the vice president of Friends of the Coleman.
Okay, I'm just going to let you hold that and reel this fan on either side.
Thank you very much. Thank you very much.
Okay, item four is public input and unscheduled personal appearances and you want to
audience wish to address the council on any of the agenda items.
There will be none. I am five as a consent agenda.
Staffers are recommending item six to 13 for the consent agenda.
If you take a quick look at those and then if there are no questions about any of them
within our time, the motion to approve the consent agenda as recommended.
And do we have a second? Second. Will call please.
Work it for us, sir. All right.
All right. Tetses item 14, Miami Public School, Bond Presentation.
So, if we're going to hold this here tonight or educate this all and hopefully everyone watching
know that the bond issue is coming up. These are the new ones.
These are the new ones. They're a little, they're legal.
Want to be recognized on the people you will.
Anybody pass them out?
Want to keep on breaking it up?
This is my third time of the presentation.
Oh, it is out. Three times.
That's a question.
You've heard you say you've heard this one three times?
Yeah, so I get to vote three times.
It's my old Chicago time.
Well, take that.
There we go.
First, I'd like to talk about our bond proposal.
Back then, I think it was the fun.
I keep forgetting I'm not using a Mac.
So, it's a little background here.
We had a committee that started working over 18 months ago.
We built a long-range travel crew with Hawaiian foot school district
because we talked about facilities.
This kind of side by side piece.
What's our strategic plan?
Look at all of our facilities.
You know, can't it give us what's a lot of the expense of our facilities?
What are the current issues?
We're facing our facilities.
looking at the resources that we're allocating each facility.
I'm trying to ensure we're operating specifically as possible.
And then again, possibly set forth a long range capital improvement plan.
And so we did all that, looked at all of our data from staffing,
to what it cost to run it.
We pulled issues of facilities.
And one of the things stood out automatically to the committee,
and we already knew it was with the passage of 2016 bond issue.
We didn't invest a lot.
And we arrived, we did update the entry,
and we arrived at the safe and secure.
And when we did that, that set us on the clock.
And the chief rights back there set us on the clock,
and of the dress and the code that she used there.
We talked about sprinkler and then we have other things outside the fire code.
Making sure we're in the positive, the H standards.
You know, we don't have the elevator in that facility to the set before or we don't.
We have to keep them from coming out and looking until there's our stairs,
don't be ADA and Pons.
With the width of them.
We have lots of other issues talking about structurally with that building.
There are a lot of issues with our plumbing, our electrical and that building.
I mentioned before, you know, we're currently with that basement issues.
We have there just our immense and worked.
You know, right now, at least in a pump.
It cost us just shot 50 dollars a year to keep that basement.
Some of the water out of the best we can.
It's just constantly filling up lots of issues there at Robotters.
So we automatically quickly determine where Rogers has to be addressed.
We got the ticking clock of meeting code.
And we also have some issues there that we can't continue to pump money.
You're in to Robotters that I'm investing in it.
And you need to prepare in the issues.
I'm moving forward in the point.
So we dove into that really looked.
And we talked about this project, which is phase one of our long-term capital proof plan.
We quickly realized that this building of built 1947 has to be addressed.
And so the options are A.
We have a lot of different entities come out and look at that and give us a quote.
What it takes to get that building up to code.
And the number we were given when they made in 680,000.
It's like 8.7 million dollars for our figure.
To get to address the structural issues, the plumbing, the electrical and the code and the components issues will go by.
That'll give you a new classroom.
That'll give you a new addition.
That's just basically giving the building up to kind of standards and addressing some of the structural issues.
And foundationally, she's did we have to go out to the middle school.
And we all concurred that wasn't a wise investment.
And that's not something we thought comfortable asking our taxpayers to invest in.
So we started making plans.
We have to be best to accommodate that 6708 greater currently our housing will Rogers.
And so in doing this, we looked a lot of different data as well, and we looked at, particularly
talking about research, is the fiscal development and social motion development of
students, of children at age, and we determined it's best to learn our sixth grade to the
fourth, the Dinnacles, and that edition there, we'll make it a fourth-fifth and sixth grade
center, and then take our seventh and eighth grade and root them out to the high school
campus.
But what we plan to do at the high school campus is re-purpose to turn high school a little bit,
I'll remodel it, and then make that a junior high, a 789, and build an edition off the
high school for, for, potentially, 12.
So I put everything, 7 to 12 to 1 campus, you know, they would share similar facilities,
cafeteria, media center, gymnasiums, you're very as out loud facilities, it's service
you're like your ad tech and bank and local music, etc.
So that's where we're, we're at here, what we're proposing with phase one, this is the two,
two different propositions here, we got the construction piece, which I address, and included
there are storm shelters.
We also have a proposition two, which is transportation, which allow the district funding
every two years for buses.
So we'll kind of work our way through this slide presentation.
I feel like I'm, I think this is out of their asking, I think tonight, I've been
talking about things, there's been a 16th one up to now, and we still have a few more
to get out, we've got a few more to get out of, actually.
So the need for the bond issue, we kind of address that, you know, we're trying to address these
outdated buildings, we've got this capital improvement plan, I mentioned the timeline, what the cost
was, and then the purpose of purchasing buses.
I kind of flew through that, but the plan a little more in depth, I mentioned a three-phase plan,
but before I dive in here, I want you to keep in mind that phase one is what you have in the
front of you.
We do have a vision, I think that's important for us to come to our stakeholders with this
innovation and directional long-term vision direction, but phase one is we talk about
that includes what you have in front of you, and we'll be able to balance the
amount of money.
And that is addressing our six 7th and 8th grade and moving the six grade into Nichols, elementary
upper elementary, and our 7th and 8th grade to the current model high school side, and we would
provide that to have a model of junior high and a model high school.
Transportation, the way that's funded, is this $1.2 million in total, spread out in the last
year, so every year, we do have that model of exception in the last year, year 14, year
or $0.000 for transportation, and we do have a phase two, as we looked at these facilities,
and what we're asking, we're asking for the necessities here, we recognize that we have
many experiences to improve, which is good.
That's something district has experience.
experience in a long time.
Matter of fact, this is the first time in eight years, and we've started to school here
at the more you're in more kids and you're in the previous year with, and he's such
for a month, month was in growth, and our student loan numbers.
We also have been tracking all of that as we've talked about, our success value got the district,
and we're that's going, we're that's adding, really in about eight years we filled with
that student growth and then you can kind of add a few classrooms, a couple of sites, and
we feel we can do that, training that out in about eight years and have attached things,
and said, we are finished too, and we can come back and look at some of the dishes that
need to take place because of the student growth.
And there are last phase of this long-term capital approved plan.
Again, this is not included in this current proposal, would be when this bond issue falls off,
so in 13 years ago to move, and build the books, and 14 to be a new lower elementary school.
I mentioned all this plan, because this has been something we've worked up for a long time,
and the purpose of this is to be as efficient as possible.
We go with this plan, we go from eight school sites to four, and at two locations, we have essentially
our pre-cate through sixth grade, where we have this side of town, and our 7-12 on this side of town.
And that would say a lot of overhead costs to the district, approximately $500,000,
the nutrition is playing, and we deal with, you know, re-hired positions, there are need counselors,
school-based social workers, help the offset, maybe some of our pre-cores and course offerings,
and like the courses we've got in the past, because the budget cuts, more resources to the classroom,
and things that made you the week you trimmed down by going from eight sites to four sites, over that time period.
So big question, I kind of laid off with tax increase, it is tax increase, 16%, the building project of it is $19,000,
and $30,000, and the transportation is $1.2, the median progress property tax in our school district is $52 per year,
and what that equates out to is $3.74 a month, okay?
Now obviously you may fall somewhere different on that scale, and this kind of lives it out for you,
we put it as what's it on the cost, you know, each year, that doesn't go up each year,
that's consistent to up life of it, is the 14 year series bond with that kind of lives you would should monthly,
I can get the district budget monthly, that's why I look at it, and we've got those conversations with the family as well.
So again, I've kind of done most of this, I'm not going to dive into this a whole lot that we talk about,
you know, that campus of the junior high in the high school, kind of what we would get there.
We're trying to be very efficient here and share our common spaces.
We're not building a cafeteria.
We're not building a gymnasium, a new auditorium.
We're talking about classrooms.
We are talking about tornado shelters.
That would provide this body she provided that for all.
All students in 4th to 12th grade at those facilities.
1200 housing per 1200 at the Mama High School campus.
And then housing per 750 at the Nichols campus.
At the Nichols campus.
And things that we do.
One more to learn to work with our local emergency management team.
So we've got that process.
We've got that for the community.
And that's something we recognize and we're not cleaning as well.
I'm hoping this is going to play.
This is a fly by of the high school.
If you're a visual person like me, this will be the...
That's probably one computer.
Jeremy, point out on there where the current front door is.
So this right here.
If you're right here with these people, we're walking in.
That's the current front entry.
And everything you see here is a new two-story bill.
As you can get into play, I've got to dress that.
I've been asked why two stories.
Well, I simply is it.
Downside is the footprint that building.
But also saves us a couple of thousand dollars using the heart deck of the tomato shelter.
As a foundation, that we have to build out the side there to expand and wire.
So in that's something we thought was very efficient.
This will be the new junior high entry to the past.
Down that into parking drop-off lanes.
For the junior high, again, same facility to keep in those kids separated.
Much is possible.
You see, this is the front entry of the high school, the current front entry.
Everything that comes out there is a new bill.
When you think safe rooms, it's not just completely concrete.
There are some windows in those rooms.
They do have to store doors to shut.
They're a favorite rated for F-5-20A to inside there.
They'll save rooms.
Some of the garbage that have changed since last time I've built over the facility,
which is about five, six years ago.
There's now that they have to have an old power source.
They're on the front middle of two hours.
So, you know, an event of 20A, a new power.
You're going to close the room.
That's not on my power when I promise you.
And that's that room.
Power source.
Power goes out.
And also, they have that restroom inside there.
And so, you're just stretching your safe rooms.
It does drive your cost up a little bit.
This is kind of a forefling.
You look at here.
So, what you see essentially from,
there's the existing administration entry.
And if you're here over, that's going to be our seven day,
do not classroom facilities.
Your entrance is again on this end.
You can kind of see some of these.
great area is here and here is we've talked about the possible phase two projects and then everything from here down will be the first floor
I'm blocking the audience first floor of the 10 to 12 and this is the second story that goes here
We will come back and this would be our ag and tech at rooms out here in the annex
I currently house that but we do have speech and debate drama out here those are moving side of the high school
and then we would read part of some of the current fine arts space
through here to expand that as you talk about operating more sections of 7 to 7 to 12
That's kind of an idea of the four plans and what the again my my high school junior high campus would look like
Nicko's up a lot of entry again before through six grade with ten classroom edition
These are all turn key operations and talk about your building build and you want to build a building that's when it's done you're ready to move in
Meaning it's got the next day student desk
The smart board or technology that's needed hooked up projectors
All those materials to the teacher desk
You're the next day of cabin tree and stuff for storage and stuff to take place your classrooms
This will show us the amount they don't begin here
We'll go back home
You may have time to play
I must see them
That's why
This will be a kind of fly by of nickels
You've been able to notice we built a new media center there that last bondage in 2016
And so what you see in the Browns and current facility in the blue roof is a new addition
And that's what really do that media center that blue roof
Those rock roofs are not something that's popular
And very efficient anymore
Metal roofs are often popular
Something that's all lasting
And this does include safe rooms, the toilet of shelters
Inside nickels
And this allows them to move the sixth, sixth grade over to nickels
Has all the blue roof and the instruction Jeremy?
All the blue roof and the new construction
And so the media center was
The media center was new construction for 2016 bondage
And it's somewhere else
The media center?
Yeah
I mean is it part of that blue roof or
Now it's up here when you see this crusher here
It's in the front
Okay
Thanks in the south
It's the front entry
Okay
And how many classrooms, I guess, should there be a good?
There is 10 classrooms here, so here's a footprint of it.
It's also designed for future builds off there as well.
So you've got 10 classrooms, all these in the center.
The classroom is the whole way.
The rest room is all inside the tornado shelter.
Just as I mentioned with the high school in the house,
750 in there.
Now, this is current.
This is just possible, but it doesn't exist in it.
This happens, that would be something that, well, we'd like to do,
and then we could build off that for the elementary, and it can take,
you know, take advantage of a multi-use facility used by multiple grades,
multiple schools, trying to minimize a cost.
So we got seven teachers right now.
Those are not cheap to run.
And so this is, hopefully, through the first few things,
they can stand to serve us a whole all of our students.
So I'm going to go to the next slide.
I know there's a few, probably, some questions you want to ask,
but I want to take a look at it.
Thank some of the things I've heard, as we kind of have to address,
number one, the videos there, the pristine,
green around and voting in architects, because on those,
they have your architectural drawings.
They don't have to fill these around you that you don't know.
And so they don't show all of that.
And it's that way.
It's, we look at, we're not trying to fold the voters.
You know, and make it like it's an open pasture or open green area.
They think people can even understand that.
And hopefully, I understand where I'm trying to fold the world over there.
I, as they know, what's around those facilities.
What they're located at.
We're about to just build schools and talk about criminal writers.
A lot of the question, what we're going to do is we're going to do it for the Rogers.
And so what we're going to have to do is demolish the whole front half of the Rogers.
Over half of it.
Every time the base, whatever thing from the gym to the south.
And back to the cafeteria, we have to be demolished.
We're going to try to incorporate some of the features.
Himalagers, the entrance of those things into the new build.
That's important.
We can incorporate some of those little bit of the old into the new.
Keep your current students.
They respect and understand.
You know, where it's come from and what's been through.
Other people went through those hallways.
We've keep the gymnasium.
When I go into the gymnasium, they have that go through.
We have a lot of issues already.
Practice space and time.
And that movement that's set today.
The highest will will help tremendously.
We need to keep that facility.
And also probably use that because of education courses at Nichols during the daytime.
And because of expanding the heating space out at Nichols, we'll keep the cafeteria.
It's, you know, one of the newest additions onto your Rogers.
We keep that to prep food.
Out of until we come back and build it.
As I've showed a few of those is that Nichols up the down rows,
70 years.
And keep that.
I had a prep to go at cafeteria and have to ship that across the road for students.
They're at nickels.
That's just trying to keep those.
Making sure we're dealing with the necessities of the classrooms, first and foremost,
because you see the construction dollars and you start adding on cafeterias and gym
80's, you see those things that nature's going to drive that up considerable.
And we recognize that we have responsibility to, you know, tax increases are not fun,
which should have minimized as much as possible and dealing with necessities and development.
Again, it's about the long range of planning, you know, for your community.
So that's got a lot of big things I've been hit with and I get out and speak to groups
as things to be repetitive and everybody has speak to and talk to about those facilities
and kind of the plan itself.
And again, I want to re-hash reiterate that the difference of the 2015 bond issue that failed
for the elementary school and this one is one building in the school, because that's an necessity.
You know, we have to address the six out of the ninth grade.
We could build it all in a bunch of school and remember six out of the eighth grade to the current elementary
but that's not my arping, you know, why isn't best, why isn't a little bit of a district's part in good for kids?
Because you have to move each grade to grade into very self-interest school and that be a significant challenge
kind of there.
In a sense, you wouldn't cut any of your heavy cost savings or fish to save yourself.
I'd love to a lot to take in.
With respect to time, I've already done it quicker than I normally have.
I normally have various speaking engagements, but I'd be glad to get any questions.
I'm not curious about the safe rooms.
Do those have to be left clear and available, of course, for an emergency or can they be used?
They're used in the classroom.
They are in the classroom.
So it's actually a classroom that you use because, you know, in all honesty, besides you drills,
what required you so many drills to a semester, and you talk about tornado drills, and then
should have been happened, you know, it's middle time.
So you see some districts have built a tornado shelter that maybe it's only purpose.
But we really felt we needed something that's going to be used, and we're going to be efficient.
We haven't, and you see, you see this, you see this quite a bit as well.
So it's a classroom that you use on daily basis, and the hallway and the restrooms.
And we've got a plan in place to deal with in student information, student records,
and things that nature shouldn't be that, that you need to use the facility.
Okay.
Any questions in the air?
On proposition 2 in the Garsons School Busons, can you, you've talked a lot about the other stuff?
Can you do a little bit of detail as I mean, how many buses are we, I know that you're saying
so much a year, but how many can you buy?
Well, with what you, way you have a set of stuff.
Yeah, we were talking about that, you know, process of,
things can go up over the years.
Recently, we purchased buses in a good different
collectible by shaving forward or dives.
They do very little bit about price.
We tend to like international buses.
We have a little bit of a lot of them here.
Plus, we've been serviced here a lot closer.
We don't misshift on the Tulsa for service.
Like we've been doing some of the two more of the toughest buses.
So we've tended to go with them and in the last purchase around, they were around
$80 to $83,000 for buses and you get electric buses.
Those are going to be closer to $90, those will make it all over.
Those are the white ones we know that we have because those are air conditioned.
So you don't pay a little more for those.
They're smaller buses.
We have such as we have a handy cat bus.
I think it's a 20, see the 24 or 26 passenger bus with a lift on it.
That was about $60,000, you know, there.
We do have a 14 passenger bus, what all three?
Those, I think that was about $42,000 somewhere down there.
It just varies on the size of the capacity you get.
You can actually get buses with less and more capacity than we have.
But your turn of 1000 is kind of what you would hope you'd do out the project, purchase
a couple of buses with, and if there's money left over, you can use that to install cameras,
a range of camera equipment and stuff to buses.
You can also bank that for future news, you know, carry that up with additional money.
The reason we're asking for that is, you know, it's very small percentage, matter of fact, it's
five.
Right about five percent, a little more of the districts in the state that fund bus, turn in the
purchase, pay, and you can do a few dollars.
And general funds are major operating funds, you know, in our district, and we've allocated
tradition through the year, we purchased a bus, and it's suburban about most years.
We haven't been able to do that for less few years, but most of the years you look back to
basically something that's done out of the general fund.
And so that takes the same size of about $110,000, it could be allocated to the classroom, you
know, whether that's decreasing by the size of the primary source of your classroom, etc.
And so, you know, we're trying to get with that train a little bit and fund that to
a lot of funds, something that's very common, you know, the percentage at five, oh five percent
of schools that don't find it to a lot of funds, it's actually less than that the fund
of the jump fund, because there are some that have a county sales tax that they fund, a transportation
period.
A lot of the county council is one of those that are bad, but it isn't, they're all, they're
funded to the tax, it's just been a property tax or sales tax.
And so that's why we brought forward proposition too, is to hear how people.
to play it up, it's not something we see on Jerry Wajig
who will continue with our general fund.
With the answer question.
Because I think a lot of people need to get educated on what
a bus truly costs.
Because I think a lot of people have zero.
I didn't.
I mean, I thought a lot of equipment lately,
and I never thought about a bus cost.
But in talking about the buses and with the changes,
here you guys kind of get a transportation study of how
the flow around.
Because if anybody ever has,
has never been over there to drop a kid off.
I'll let you take my child and do that.
And you'll see, I mean, it's become very organized.
Because it's firstly year, it's always crazy,
because people are new and no.
So I'm just curious.
With this removal of the will Rogers.
Will that help you guys?
I mean, you don't have as many.
So that's got to go somewhere else.
And I just was curious.
Yes.
It will.
Because what Rogers, we would really change our transportation
off last couple of years.
Trying to help them.
We do.
The traffic.
It can be a little heavy.
Particularly talk about remote providers and vehicles.
Right.
I think I'll get some traffic jam.
But that's just because it's kind of lamb locked.
Most of the others are pretty quick.
And now, there's a little rush period of 10, 15 minutes at most.
But yeah, it gets backed up.
And you can find yourself setting up there for.
Not doing anything.
Not only bring us up because I would feel that it could help.
Not only the buses, not only the transportation piece.
But more so I think we look at these facilities.
You know, we're redesign and drop off and pick up areas.
Parking safety of it.
Because you know, we're trying to be more efficient.
Because you know, last thing we used to get a key, I mean,
and so we always look at that.
We're, we're the possibility of a, you know, come back and the city always
works well with this.
And this is closing for that section in front of Nichols often.
You know, when you're treating a drop off pickup lane.
It's used on a certain time.
And so there's different options that we're working at.
We're designing this.
But, you know, as you talk about taking the six six.
Great vehicles instead of taking the high school.
It would help dramatically.
You're full of traffic flow around that area.
Now, as we talk about the school, the job off pickup from parents or buses.
That's some things when you're parking your job off pickup.
Things don't really need that.
You may have mentioned it, but in phase one, given that this fund does pass.
How long will that take for completion?
So, they, you know, passes May 14.
But after that, you get the architects really get down.
Because they aren't paid until it's, until it's passed.
None of them are.
So they're not, they've given us some conceptual drawings.
Some things I get.
But they're really down into all the drawings.
Not too long after the pass into that.
So that's, that's still a lot of profit.
that's there and it goes to check points, make sure everything's approved and you're ready to go.
And you would seek a round break until probably somewhere in five to six months after the past
attack.
And then you're looking at about a year and a half somewhere around there, depending on whether
you need to complete it.
So what I would say, what I've been told is expect to move in in a 21-22 school year.
So essentially, the group that's freshman right now,
finished their freshman year in high school, they need senior movement that
need facility.
You know, they need to take advantage of that.
Now, there's a possibility it could be a semester,
logistically that could be a nightmare.
Switching buildings and grades, but that's a best case scenario,
but we are fully our plan to shoot a pass and is to,
you know, what plan do you have for the 21-22 school year,
moving those buildings?
Any other questions?
Any one in the audience have any questions?
Okay, Jeremy, thank you very much.
Thank you, everyone.
Just go vote on May 14.
And I apologize, Lee, but I have to get this opportunity.
That's quite hard.
I'm not wearing a sport coat there, though.
Thanks, Jeremy.
Thank you.
Okay, I'm 15.
You perform a presentation by Crawford and Associates.
But the right is back with us tonight.
Good evening.
Nice to be back again.
It's good to see you all.
What you have in front of you?
Any way I'm hoping you can.
Is everyone been through a performer?
Yes.
We're not going to go through every page.
I'm just going to get the highlight.
Thank you.
Questions about a certain page?
And we're going to be the member of a third of the performer.
What do you think it's going to get out of the line?
We'll be presenting the annual party.
On a scale of 1 to 10, how did we do?
And after being asked this question for many years,
Finally, my program, the original founder of our firm, decided to come up with a
Financial Framework where we can answer that question.
Where we can break down these reports that nobody likes to read.
And in the end, tell you on a scale of 1 to 10, this is how you can.
So we started doing this a little over 10 years ago.
And the city of Miami has been participating.
We're about 10 years.
So you have a good 10 years working to struggle that here.
You can look back on.
And so we break into the prefection.
Your financial ratios, which is how we can do in the current year.
For this particular report, we were talking about the year within the June 30th, 18.
Then we talked about your financial performance ratio.
Compare to the prior year, what more are changes and how did we do?
We go up the root of that.
And the third period, financial capability.
What is our ability to break?
or the issue debt in the future. Another way to think about that is what is our financial sustainability.
Going into the future, what can we do to continue on the current track?
So those are the three major areas. Your overall score is a 7.3 this year, which is up from a 6.0.
If you put all the categories together, they'll try to average these because we don't do that nice point of average.
Just for you know.
And one reason, if you look at your numbers over the years, this is on page 5, you had a debt last year.
And so let me remind you of two things that will affect everything we talk about.
Last year, you've got to recognize that bank bond anticipation at that went across reporting entities.
So it might everything go way down and kind of skewed all the numbers.
Okay? So that's last year when you see lots of debt last year, it related to that bond anticipation at that.
What is strange about this year is you implemented again the statement 75 other post employment benefits.
It was required that you implemented it. Everybody across the nation implemented it.
That made you bring 3.3 million dollar in line with the ability onto your financial savings.
So that mess is up your numbers because you haven't had it before.
Now you had to post another post employment benefit liability out there, but it was calculated in a completely different way.
And it was a much, much lower number, more around the $1 million dollar.
So you took a big hit getting a compliance with the new accounting standards this year.
So those are two factors you need to keep in mind because those kind of skewed your numbers because of things that happen.
We're going to skip over unless you have a question to take 7.
So the fact that we're saying is that 7.3, you can't really compare it to previous years because of those two years.
You're back up compared to prior year, but last year you took a big hit because of that bond anticipation at refinancing.
Because you issued a lot of debt to get that off the book across the reporting entities.
So it kind of skewed how everything will clear last year.
And if we hadn't had to implement the gas be guidelines that 7.3 would unquestionably have been hard.
Don't know how much but somewhat hard.
Yes.
But you want to comply with the gas beets.
You want to comply with the gas beets.
So just the future and you want to issue debt and you want to get rated debt.
That's one thing your bond rating agencies look like.
Have you implemented the gas statement that's going to come out?
And that's something they look, or so you want to make sure you're current on those things.
And to make sure that you're level with unrestricted net position.
This basically says, after we take all of our assets and take out all of the utilities and anything that's restricted, what do we have left over?
And yours has gone negative this year.
It was negative last year, but it's even 10 to 16 percent this year.
And that is because we've got gas be 75 on.
We get that huge liability onto your financial statements.
So you could a liability out there that has no asset to offset it.
And you take it good for it.
This everybody has this.
you need city, every city had to do this, so everybody has the same effect.
Some of them are much bigger than what yours were, so that's not a bad thing.
On page 8, you're unassigned general fund balance.
Unassigned general fund balance, what is that?
Your general fund is your main operating fund of the city.
It operates your place, your fire, your parks, those type of activities.
And this is what we say, if we take out any money that's legally restricted for certain purpose, grant money you have on hand,
any revenues you pass that are restricted for certain purpose, what you have left to carry over into the next year.
That's what your unassigned general fund balance is.
And we like to look at that.
And there is no set standard, but there's just a general standard out there that you always want to keep at it about 10% of your revenues.
You guys have dipped to 9%.
I'm not freaking out of your 9% because you do have a rainy day fund.
But, you would still want to try to target to get that back up a little bit.
And there's a couple things you need to think about here.
You do have that rainy day fund sitting out there.
If you look at this chart in the years where it has spiked, it has spiked because you sent more money over from the MSU.
Is my understanding you have passed an ordinance that has put a limit on how much it will send over.
So just know, you just can't randomly say, well, just send an MSU rate money over to help.
Step that number of people.
Because you guys have passed an ordinance to a limit that amount.
So you're at 9%.
That's not terrible.
But you probably want to try to get that up just a little bit.
Just so if you haven't made your disaster, you've got something that's never, but you can help pay for that disaster.
Over on page 17, you're changed in that position.
Did it go up or down?
Here's one up.
It's your last year went way down because of that debt issue.
It went up this year.
If you look down at the bottoms of the second paragraph, it will tell you that your governmental activities.
When at 1.7 million in your business type activities, which is your electorate, your water, your surrogation,
when down by half a million.
A lot of that is due to operational cost.
And it's my understanding you guys did a great increase that went into effect within the past year.
And you're using that money to do improvements.
General operations.
And you can begin your systems.
So maybe all the revenue has uploaded yet, and you are starting all of those improvements.
So you did have a dip there.
But it is very explainable as to why.
And page 21, sales tax growth.
I talk about sales tax growth because when you talk about your general fund, you're least
through fire in your park.
Your general operations.
It is funded mainly by sales tax.
So it's a very important role to do on a track.
You were up slightly to 0.8%.
That's, I mean, it's not a lot, but it's a good increase to see.
You always want to see that number.
is what sales tax does is when we have operational issue problems, so sales tax is a very important factor in global government and global government and global government.
And the other page I'm going to talk a little bit about is page 26 which has all the years on it.
And 26.7 and 28 all go together. And the question is, is if you need to fund projects in the future, you have the available debt capacity to do that.
And you do, because you have no general obligation bonds outstanding, you have no bonds outstanding, they're paid back for the property tax.
So you do have that taxing ability out there, and it requires above the citizens.
So as your general revenue bonds go up, that are backed normally by your water sewer and sanitation revenue to be paid back, you do have enough of finding things towards out there, should you ever decide if you want to go that route.
And I did the highlights, the ones that, you know, are kind of important, the ones we normally get questions about.
There is one other page that I did see it, I think my tax will all page 10, your pension plan, your pension plan, for the actual study was funded at 70% this year.
Now, that is still considered underfunded, and it's still kind of considered not favorable, but I can tell you there is not a need of a little pension plan in this state that is 100% funded.
You guys are making strides, it is improving every year.
I mean, you're putting the money into it, you've had good investment returns, and it's coming up.
And I look at a lot of these plans, both through the OMR and program and through single employer plans.
And I can tell you, 70% is a good number, because I see them a lot lower than this.
So this is not a bad number at all. And I think as you continue to do, things you've been doing, this number won't be going up.
I will answer any specific questions you have.
So when the gentleman came and talked about our audit, he also touched our rainy day fund and our reserves.
And I was going to talk about this at budget time, but since it's come up again, would we be better off?
Because when you look at the total pool of money, we've got that ratio is here, that you can count all of it.
But we've got some of it designated as 20 day fund.
Should we move some of that money over just to...
And I know it's...we had a one-focketed the other, but from the standpoint of the bond rating companies and stuff
I'm not sure how they look at that.
And it's moving some of that money might improve the way we look financially, because they don't pay attention to the rainy day fund.
They will look at that. They will look at that. They will look at the...
They will look at the day-home stabilization months.
So you have a fund that is sitting there and the case will disaster.
You have a place you think of to do the things you need to do.
So they would look at that in a whole. I can tell you the problem when if you move it back into a fun with the money it's sitting
Co-mingled with either the general fund or the energy way it tends to get
because you tend to forget it's really restricted for a certain purpose.
So that's why years ago, you guys moved it over to a separate fund so you can do,
hey, this money is set aside for disasters, for emergencies,
for those things we need outside of our regular operations.
But don't we have two of those, Dean?
One of them, you have the rainy day fund.
And then when the Arthur was here, he listed another fund
that I thought he was using in his race shows.
I don't have to go back and look at it and say.
There's three line items inside of the rainy day fund,
stabilization of emergency and R&R.
Maybe that's what you think about, because there are elements too,
but only one thing to prove about it, yeah.
So I wouldn't make any difference anyway.
Yeah.
Okay.
And it protects it from me.
So was there a, so, so page five is the overall.
Yes.
And again, we have a 720 this year that, without the gas,
the adjustment, which we all understand can't be made.
But if we're just trying to say, if we want to look back over a few years ago and say,
how are we doing long term, we probably would kind of hire a school there.
You would probably cut in it.
I would have guessed probably seven, five, seven, six.
Yeah.
The gas.
Trust me, guys.
It's not snowing down.
There's still lots of changes.
Okay.
Fortunately, the ones for 19, we'll mainly be disclosures to make this book bigger instead of smaller.
But it's what's coming next.
Thank you.
Any questions for Brenda?
Okay.
Thank you.
I don't know.
So back in November of 2018, we entered into an agreement with Miami BMX to dismantle
the track that's currently at Taylor Park.
And part of that agreement was the board to be the removal of some islands and taking
another location for storage.
Once we got started, we're using the dirt, some of the top solar and the clay.
Came to the realization that the large metal solar that's out there isn't salvageable
a net for us to haul it somewhere for storage for later use.
Fairly rest in it.
It's just not going to hold that.
Another issue that we had that we agreed to in the MOU was also dismantling the an outsourced
sand and taking it to the storage.
bookkakship and in looking at it in that over time, it's not going to come down in one piece.
So it wouldn't be sound people either.
So what we have done is we've gone back to my amyamics and discussed that with them and
came to an agreement, if you're agreeable to it, that we would take the metal cylinder and
have it salvaged in my amyamics with if the funds from whatever the value is of salvaging the metal cylinder.
And instead of the announcer stand being able to deliver that to the home of one piece,
that we would remove the signs off of that stand.
And then there's also my amyamics sign that's attached to melted over the Taylor Park sign that's in the northwest
order the part that we would remove that and those signs would go to my amyamics
for going to keep hopefully something on the use of that.
Chris, you might want to make the clear of this storage site that we agreed to is in Welch.
Is in Welch, yes.
So what we're talking about originally in our agreements, we're going to haul all of these things to Welch.
Yes.
And now getting into it, found out they're not worth hauling.
So it seems like this is a better way of doing it.
We don't have to haul it very far.
We get the scrap.
It goes to them.
And it's pretty much equitable to the original agreement.
Right.
And I don't know if you guys have been by there lately that public court system could jump
the dark in there.
There's still a little bit of dark that needs to be written in an effort to get it
found out we could remove.
There was a small storage building in the back that was really dilapidated and not were
saving either that we've been able to remove.
I did drive by there.
And I think all the dirt was repurposed for the splash pad.
And I asked that question.
Is that right?
And the dirt was taken to follow us.
But that big whistle or whatever, it was originally as huge.
And I don't know.
Is that what they just used for the jumps?
Yeah.
Like that was where the start line was.
Okay.
Last time.
I imagine that's just going to be scrap value.
Which was about $100 a ton.
So I imagine.
I know we scrap some things that work and we get to hold brisk those over and
call upon.
And they will actually come out and pick that up and then they haul it off for us.
and they just, they get the scrap value,
you just to do it for $100, it's probably better to have them
all the way.
I would, and still that thing falling off and going down the...
I would have a container truck like,
to have, I don't know, but like, it's nice that I've been
to be down in the truck.
Like a roll off container, or yeah.
We both, you moved to Athens.
Okay.
I'm not trying to tell you job, and just,
I'm glad I'm not done it.
Yeah.
And they will receive the money.
So part of the work in effort in this was getting this close to that,
and then, you know, thinking that out,
and trying to come up with an equitable agreement with you.
I assume they bought the whistle originally?
Yes.
Yeah.
All of that, all of the stuff that's there,
at the park, was stuff that they brought in.
I'm glad.
Yeah.
Are there plans to go into recondition that, and put it back as a park,
has it originally was?
Our hope is to recondition it and turn it maybe into a dog park.
We're keeping, so there's a fence.
There's, like, an eight or a tenth of a fence.
I can't remember exactly the height.
That's, chain link around it.
So we're leaving that.
There's already water and lighting there at the park that was
pinnled for the BMX, which are things that you need for a dog park.
And so we're, we're, we're, we're the bike for the community to have a dog park.
We're looking at it because we're grants to a pipe.
We have a dog park that would be a good use of that right there,
because it is located in the floodplain that would be a good use
in a community and we would be able to utilize also.
We'll question.
Do you need concerns about the amendment?
Do we have a question of what is amendment?
I'll make a motion.
In a second?
A second?
A little ballpoint.
Work it.
I'm forster.
Thank you.
That's Christian.
Adam 17 is mayor's knowledge to appoint the hospital,
the My Omega Community Facilities Authority.
We're placing the old Johnson and Bill's term would expire 5, 1, 2, 3,
as you know.
He was a council representative on that body.
And in even after he went off the council, he continued for about six months,
I think, to serve in that capacity, which I appreciate it,
because he's been there from the beginning.
But he decided to, he wanted to resign and go off into private life completely.
And so, I would like to.
you got to consider my nomination and be all for that position. If you, as a reminder, there's
a seven-member group, there are two members that represent the high school, which is the
superintendent and the athletic director of superintendent and school board and school board member.
Thank you. And then there's two members that represent the college, which is Dr. Hale and the athletic
director, I guess he's not the athletic director, but it's just in this case. And then Stacey
Sarawatt is the athletic director, and then there's two members that represent the city,
different than the mayor and a council member, or the council's designated me.
And so I don't think anybody here was interested in doing that. I did talk to Brian about it.
I mean, he has some commitments. And I knew that everybody else was pretty busy, so I approached the bill,
and the bill was very involved in the fundraising for the Steve Olon Statue, and of course,
a long time community member. And I talked with him about understanding that he would be on there to
represent the city's point of view. I mean, we're all worked together very well on that group,
but it is important that the different interests are equally represented, and the bill understands
that would be his responsibility. So any questions? If not, ask you to consider that.
My recommendation.
I'll make a motion, yeah.
I'll make a motion.
And we have a second.
Oh, call, please.
Foraster?
What's this?
All right.
All right. Thank you.
Item 19 is new business. Any new business, anyone?
Item 19, staff reports or new packets, that's available if there are any questions.
Item 20 is Mayor Council Community announcement. Some of you already mentioned earlier that the
Coleman birthday is this Thursday, and I encourage everyone to come out.
And we need to get a ticket to see the Wizard of Oz for a dollar to dress up if you want. If you don't want
to dress up as a character, come with a gleam.
Well, that's not really part of it. It's common.
And that's the only announcement I had. Anybody else have anything?
Item 21 is any manager for the negation?
I have kind of one thing that leads to another, but leads to another.
And I'd like to talk about it very quickly. Originally, I'd hope tonight
to be able to give you a definitive update on where we are on the Main Street Improvement Project.
We did finally get away from the State of Historic Preservation Office that there was one concern
that, and that's called Ship of First Short, and they're involved for two reasons. Number one,
this project from first street to the river of tracks is primarily in an historic district,
especially with the Coleman Theatre. Secondly, there's a half million dollar grant for
we'll go toward this as well. So we need to follow their regulations in order to get a half million
dollars toward this project, which is very important. They had a concern about some of the islands
that were designed for the intersection to replace the stop sign that's in the middle of the intersection.
We originally designed a very similar to what we have at Central and Maine, and their concern
was the situation in which that you can't use historic type funding for something that is not
historic. And that's a new type of design that they did not want that money to go for that.
What currently also is working with ODOT right now is to say, if we were to do that intersection,
that segment of the intersection with local money, would that be acceptable? And we think that's
going to be an approved location. So if everything works out and we get approval from ODOT to get started,
we are ready to go out to bed almost immediately. And one of our schedules right now is to maybe be able to
bring a bid to you by about the 16th of May. Now that just depends on how quickly ODOT is going to
move on it, so that could get pushed back a little bit. That's a major project that we want to
get taken care of this year. So anyway, I wanted to bring everybody up to speed because I know that
part of Main Street's in a horrendous condition. In fact, in our Facebook page, I might take a look at it,
because we mentioned this pop-hole season and asked people to guess suggestions. Last I saw,
I think we're up to about 195 posts on the Facebook page. And a lot of them mentioned Main Street.
So we are working on that and trying to get that taken care of now. So that kind of leads into
something I wanted to mention. Next week, we have a study session and we ought to also schedule some
budget. And this issue with Main Street is one of our big rocks right now. Trying to make sure that we
have money to do this project. The budget is in relatively good shape except for something like that.
What I'd like to ask you is that next week instead of trying to schedule three of our formal
budget meetings. What we'd like to do is at our study session, kind of give you an overall view of
where we're at. We do have a few issues and a few items that we're still working on. One, I think we're
going to be talking about tomorrow at the MCBB more coordinating on some of the revenues that have been
declining in CBB because of some of the hotel collections that have taken place. And these are some things
we're just going to have to take care of and deal with and we're in that process right now. So we'd like to
give you an update next week and where we're at and then maybe schedule our more formal budget meetings
in the middle of May or just shortly after the first of May. You know, I'll become the first week in May.
Just to remind you, we have to have the budget done seven days before the end of the fiscal year and that's
July 1.
There's still ample time to be able to sit down, get into the detail with the budget, but some of these issues right now.
We're not sure we're going to have a lot of good information for you next year or next week.
So we'd like to kind of schedule that around so we have that ability.
Dean, on that seven days, are there also some posting requirements two weeks before exactly that?
I understand even after you post it, there can be changes to that.
We have to have it final enough to post it.
So really we're talking about roughly three weeks before.
Yeah, the end of the year.
But still we're talking about about three weeks before those dates.
Right.
About what we would have for me.
So we still think we're in a very comfort zone on being able to talk to you about budget.
But these are just some of the issues right now with Jill and Mike and we're working with the department head saying,
you know, we might have another cut here and there.
But we're probably going to have an idea of where we're at.
I'm carry forward by tomorrow.
We have one of our kind of milestones and we'll have a much better idea of where we're at probably after some of that work tomorrow.
So still a little bit more of a work and progress, but you know, we're feeling good about that.
So anyway, the third thing that leads into is talking about mainstream and talking about that development.
But I don't think we talked about it normally as a group.
But I think I'll let you know, the Shannon Duhanna's leading us.
Shannon is his last day as a 26.
And in talking with Amanda about this and looking at the way kind of the organizational structure was when I came on board.
I had wanted to look at the possibility of us getting a little bit more involved at the MDRA,
which really focuses right now most than on the Coleman.
To look at some of the other things that are going on downtown.
And I want to make it crystal clear for anybody watching this.
I know rumors flowed around on something like this.
This is nothing to do with any dissatisfaction on my part on what Shannon has done.
Shannon has done a tremendous job at Coleman.
And we're going to miss him greatly.
And it's overseen by Amanda in the CBB and Amanda does a tremendous job.
You know, I think the world would hurt.
But I'll use a Branson analogy.
The CBB gets somebody to the door of the theater.
But once they go through the theater, then it's up to the theaters to what kind of experience that person has.
And I'd like to have a little different focus for the Coleman.
And I've asked Marsha and Marsha somebody I've known over background.
And we're at a point of a lot of change in this organization.
Marsha is going to be facing some change in the library.
We're a few key personnel that are about to retire.
And she's promised me that she's going to be here quite a while longer.
So what I've asked her to do because she's done a lot of work with the mural fest, with the cultural district that's being developed.
You know, we had a presentation.
just a little bit ago about the new pocket part in the art part that's being developed, that
like the C Coleman and not take away from the mission of the Coleman in any way shape or form,
but like to see that more into part of the cultural work that we've been doing as a community
and how that works into downtown Rita Bell.
And I asked Marcia, it's not just Marcia, of course, because she has a team with a library that can help out
if she would help oversee that and she's agreed to that.
So when you look at the budget this year, we're going to create a department of small
or library arts and culture, not just library.
But with that, we still are going to be filling the position we're calling the manager.
We'll talk to people.
They said, let me know.
We definitely need a Coleman manager.
Somebody to look over the Coleman.
We've already put out our notification to fill that position as well.
We've talked about this at MDA.
And DRA, excuse me, yesterday at our meeting.
We're going to talk to Jane and the quick about this, with the friends of the Coleman,
as to what we're working on.
I think we need to talk to friends of the library and to make sure that they're at the speed of the library
for us.
Well, we'll be taking care of that.
So it's a minor change.
I know it's talking to Amanda.
She said, thank you because she's kind of a lot of work and a lot of work to do.
So anyway, these are some modifications for making an organization.
I think it's going to make a lot stronger.
That's why we're going to talk to you to CVB tomorrow.
CVB will be talking to them tomorrow.
They have to read them.
I'm not trying to take it personally.
As chair and CVB to find out that we're no longer going to be overstating that.
It's going to be, you know, I'm excited to see what's to come.
I think, you know, if I visit a mayor today briefly,
it's an undertaking to manage to business with itself.
And I always feel that if you talk tourism in my area, one of the things that everybody looks at,
is that.
So, you know, CVB being part of tourism.
So, but I'm excited to see what you, you know, come down to that.
That's all.
All right.
Anything else, Dean?
That's it.
Okay.
I'm going to show you why a gym does.
We have a gym.
Okay.
So, I don't have 22 important stuff.
Then this meeting will be continued from council chambers.
And we can be moving on one for the purpose of executive session.
And we'll be a journeying from there also with everyone's education.
So, let's head to meeting one.
What do you need?
You need to have that.